{
  "reference_number": "9504",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a goal to reach net zero emissions by the second half of the century and the Climate Change Commission advises on the specific target for the Government to set later",
      "answer_index": 11,
      "notes": "Provided that the Commission is open to any future changes to scientific knowledge."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Carbon Dioxide - Reducing net carbon dioxide emissions to zero by 2050",
      "answer_index": 13,
      "notes": "The target must exclude enteric methane and other agricultural emissions as much as possible- in years to come food production will\n\n become a priority."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions (including from new forest planting) and using some emissions reductions from overseas (international carbon units) that have strong environmental safeguards",
      "answer_index": 2,
      "notes": "Benefits from plantation forestry, as opposed to regenerating natural forest, are dubious. Purchase of international credits will buy NZ\n\n more time in which to make appropriate decisions."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "We live in interesting times. Anything is possible- war, plague and other upheavals. NZ's contribution to global emission is so small (\n 0.17%) as to be insignificant. It would be foolish to commit NZ to a target that was either unachievable or damaging out of proportion\n to the benefits accruing."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - each incoming Government should have the option to review the third budget in the sequence",
      "answer_index": 14,
      "notes": ". All NZ law is subject to the whims of Parliament, which is in turn answerable to the electorate, at intervals of not more than three\n years. To presume that the present electorate or parliament is more knowledgeable or superior to those that come later is extreme\n arrogance."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "All NZ law is subject to the whims of Parliament, which is in turn answerable to the electorate, at intervals of not more than three\n\nyears. To presume that the present electorate or parliament is more knowledgeable or superior to those that come later is extreme\narrogance."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The government may set the plans, but it will be over to the private sector to implement them, and absorb or pass on associated\ncosts. High compliance costs may threaten the survival of some business sectors. It will need to be a function of government to\nassess the value of various sectors to NZ, and apply emissions credits accordingly. Transport and agriculture, for example, could be\n\nawarded a higher priority than tourism."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": "The Commission should have no role at all other than advisory- all decisions should be the prerogative of the government of the day."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "At least two of the proposed commissioners should have demonstrable practical experience in land management."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "If the Zero Carbon Bill becomes law it will seek to chart NZ's course from its present level of carbon emissions to those considered\ndesirable and achievable by 2050. The circumstances that will prevail in 2050 are unknowable. It will be the function of interim\n\ngovernments to continue to monitor the desirability and achievability of the 2050 target, NZ's progress towards achieving it ( or its\nrevised iteration), and its effects on NZ's citizens."
    }
  ]
}
